Guide to the William Blathwayt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1646-1796; Series I; 4.0' (10 boxes)
  - Ruvigny and Raineval, Henri de Massue de Ruvigny, 2nd Marquis of, 1648-1720
    - 10 ALS (in French) to William Blathwayt, Turin and the Camp at Scalingue, 1694 Jun 23/
      - deserters, describing the national, Jul 20/30
      - background of the troops of the Alliance, and commenting favourably on the English envoys in Switzerland, Heunniguen and d'Arselliers. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. Heunniguen, Philibert de Hervart, Baron de. 3. Arsellière, Gaspard Perrinet Arselliers, Marquis d'
    - 16 ALS (in French) to William Blathwayt, Turin and various military camps, 1694 Jul 23/ (Box 7, Folder 152)
      - Reporting the developments of the, Aug 2-Sep 18/28
      - summer campaign and the role of the Irish troops under O'Donnell. Accompanied by a letter of one Reinand requesting permission to go to Holland and by two pages of undated memoranda by Galway. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. O'Donnell, Hugh Balldearg, d. 1704. I. Reinand, Mons.
    - 12 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt (in French), Turin, Berne, and Vevey, 1694 Sep 22/ (Box 7, Folder 153)
      - About payment of troops, the, Oct 2-1694/5
      - condition of the regiments, Irish, Dec 22/Jan 1
      - troops, and Swiss Cantons. Accompanied by copies of a letter to Count Benzo, 1694 Nov 14 and to O'Donnell. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. Benzo, Count. 3. O'Donnell, Hugh Balldearg, d. 1704.
    - ALS (in French) to William III, Au camp d'Orbassan, 1694 Aug 24/
      - Concerning the Pope's decree against, Sep 3
      - the Duke of Savoy's edict for re-establishing the Vaudois. 1. Victor Amadeus I, King of Sardinia, 1666-1732. 2. Waldenses-- Piedmont. 3. Innocentius XII, Pope, 1615-1700.
    - 2 letters (copies) to Admiral Russell, Turin, 1694 Aug 6/16-
    - Discusses orders for the Fleet and its, 18/28
    - role in the strategy for the War of the Grand Alliance. 1. Orford, Edward Russell, Earl of, 1653-1727. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697.
    - "Accompt of money Received & paid by Lord Galway", Turin, 1694 Dec 18/28 (Box 7, Folder 154)
      For his military expenses in 1693, docketed by Blathwayt. 1. Great Britain. Army.
    - 22 ALS (in French) to William Blathwayt Frankfurt, Blathwayt, Zurich, Turin, and the camp before Casal, 1694/5 Jan 22-
      - Concerning commissions for his, Jun 10/20
      - officers, O'Donnell and Irish forces, Swiss troops, and preparations for and the carrying out of the Siege at Casal. Accompanied by an ALS from Ruvigny's secretary, Bouhéreau, 1695 May 20/30. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. O'Donnell, Hugh Balldearg, d. 1704. I. Bouhéreau, Elias.
    - ALS (in French) to Sir John Trenchard, Turin, 1695 Apr 25/ (Box 7, Folder 155)
      - Concerning English charity for the, May 5
      - Vaudois. 1. Trenchard, John, Sir, 1640-1695. 2. Waldenses.
    - 17 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt, Turin, Rivalta, Vevey, 1695 Aug 3/13-
      - Reporting a council of war, the, Dec 21/31
      - destruction of Casal, winter quarters, and the Duke of Savoy's plans for reforming two regiments under English pay, with acknowledgement of the King's order in the matter. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - 16 ALS, 1 LS, and 1 letter (copy) to William Blathwayt, (in French), Turin and the camp at Moncallier, 1695/6 Dec 31/ (Box 7, Folder 156)
      - Reporting payment of troops, Jan 10-1696
      - preparations for the summer campaign, May 30/Jun 9
      - and the march of the French forces into the Piedmont. The copied letter of 26 May/5 Jun has a cover letter by Galway's secretary, Bouhéreau. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. I. Bouhéreau, Elias.
    - 22 ALS, 3 LS, and 1 letter (copy) and 1 letter (extract) to William Blathwayt, (in French), Turin, Montcallier, Chivas, 1696 Jun2/12 (Box 7, Folder 157)
      - Writing about the summer campaign and, Aug 7/17
      - his growing realization of the duplicity of the Duke of Savoy. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. Victor Amadeus I, King of Sardinia, 1666-1732.
    - 24 ALS and 1 LS (in French) to William Blathwayt, v.p., 1696 Aug 15/25- (Box 7, Folder 158)
      - Reporting details on the siege of, Dec 14/24
      - Valenza, the treaty of Vigevano, his desperate need for money to pay the troops, and the march to winter quarters. The LS of 1696 Aug 31 is a recommendation, in English, of Henry Nugent, an Irish soldier. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697. 2. Great Britain. Army. 3. Nugent, Henry.
    - 2 ALS (in French) to William III, Camps at Moncallier and Candia, 1696 Jun 30/ (Box 7, Folder 159)
      - Reporting the meetings of the Duke of, Jul 10-
      - Savoy with the French and the terms, Aug 28/Sep 7
      - offered for peace. 1. William III, King of Great Britain,1650-1702. 2. Victor Amadeus I, King of Sardinia, 1666- 1732. 3. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.
    - Letter (copy, in French) to the Comte de Vernon, Au Camp de Moran, 1696 Aug 30
      Declining to receive a present from the Duke of Savoy, offered in a letter from Vernon, 1696 Aug 30, a copy of which is present. 1. Vernon, Comte de. 2. Victor Amadeus I, King of Sardinia, 1666- 1732. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Savoy.
    - ALS (in French) to Lord Godolphin, Vigerano, 1696 Sep 30/
      - Need for funds to pay his troops., Oct 10
      - 1. Godolphin, Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of, 1645-1712. 2. Great Britain. Army.
    - "Declaration of my Lord Galway concerning the Brandenburg Troops": contemporary ms. (copy), Milan, 1696 Nov 13 (Box 7, Folder 160)
      Concerning their pay. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.
    - "Declaration of Lord Galway concerning the Troops": contemporary ms. (copy, in French), Milan, 1696 Nov 13
      Concerning the payment of troops after the end of the hostilities in Savoy. 1. Great Britain. Army. 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.
    - 2 letters of exchange (in French) for payment of troops, Milan, 1696
      Prepared by Lord Ranelagh and accompanied by two reports by Galway on accounts of his military expenses. 1. Great Britain. Army. 2. Great Britain. Treasury. 3. Ranelagh, Richard Jones, 1st Earl of, 1636?- 1712.
    - "A State of the Case as to the Reducement of Lord Gallway's Custodium Rents": contemporary ms. (copy), [ca. 1696]
      Accompanied by two other documents referring to Galway's lands in Ireland.
    - ALS (in French) to William Blathwayt, n.p., [1696?] (Box 7, Folder 161)
      Recommendation for M. de Reynaud. 1. Reynaud, M. de.
    - ALS (in French) to William Blathwayt, Dublin, 1698 Apr 12
      Recommending one Capt. Milborn.
    - 10 ALS and 1 LS (in French) to William Blathwayt, Dublin, 1700 Dec 26-
      - Writing with reports on regiments and, 1701 Jun 16
      - shipping and with recommendations for advancement of officers. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - Rycaut, Paul, Sir, 1628-1700
    - Collection of diplomatic papers: 6 items, 1692 (Box 8, Folder 162)
      Documents stemming from his activities as English resident in Hamburg, including Articles presented at Celle to the Representatives of England and Holland, 1692 Dec; extracts of letters from the Princes of Wolfenbüttel concerning the electorate; extract of a relation of the Brandenburg envoy at Dresden, 1692 Dec 11; and Proceedings at Hanover 1692 Jul 8: all are endorsed by Rycaut. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Hanover.
    - 3 ALS to William Blathwayt, Hamburg, 1691/2 Mar 11- (Box 8, Folder 163)
      - Reporting on negotiations for a, 25
      - treaty between Hamburg and Denmark. The letter of Mar 11 includes a copy of Rycaut's letter to Lord Sydney on Mar 8, and the letter of Mar 25 is accompanied by copies of Rycaut's letters to Sydney of 1691 Nov 13 and 24 and by the answer of the Senate of Hamburg to Rycaut 1692 Mar 25 in High Dutch, with a Latin translation. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Hamburg. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark. 3. Hamburg. Senate. 4. Romney, Henry Sydney, Earl of, 1641-1704. 5. Denmark, Treaties, etc., 1670-1699 (Christian V).
    - 7 ALS to William Blathwayt, Hamburg, 1692 Mar 18/28- (Box 8, Folder 164)
      - About English efforts to prevent a, Jul 29
      - treaty between Hamburg and Denmark, and plans to stop the trade in contraband goods in Hamburg by English merchants. The letter of Apr 5/15 is accompanied by a copy of the letter from the Senate of Hamburg to the Queen, 1692 Apr 5. 1. Hamburg. Senate. 2. Denmark, Treaties, etc., 1670-1699 (Christian V). 3. Mary II. Queen of Great Britain, 1662-1694. 4. Great Britain- -Foreign relations--Hamburg.
    - 2 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt, Hamburg, 1692 Aug 9/19-
      - Describing the fraudulence of the, Oct 4
      - Danes in negotiating their treaty with Hamburg and reporting the building of warships at Lübeck, with a draft letter of protest to the Senate of Lübeck. 1. Denmark, Treaties, etc., 1670-1699 (Christian V). 2. Lübeck. Senate.
    - ALS to James Vernon, Hamburg, 1692 Jun 24
      Concerning Irish soldiers wanting commissions in Imperial regiments and the progress of negotiations in the treaty between Hamburg and Denmark. 1. Vernon, James, 1646-1727. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Hamburg. 3. Denmark, Treaties, etc., 1670-1699 (Christian V).
  - Ryves, Thomas
    - 1 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt, Port Royal, 1686 Sep 25
      - Sending Blathwayt his salary as, 1686/7 Mar 12
      - Deputy auditor and Surveyor General of Jamaica. Ryves was Receiver General of Jamaica and he mentions an audit of his accounts. 1. Jamaica--History.
  - St. Barbe, John, bart., 1655?-1723
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Salisbury, [1702 Oct] (Box 8, Folder 165)
      Requesting a leave for Daniel Hunt, lieutenant and adjutant to the forces in New York, to recover from rheumatism. 1. Hunt, Daniel. 2. Great Britain. Army. 3. New York (State)--History-- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
  - St. Clair, Robert
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Tilbury Port, 1686 Oct 26
      Concerning officers taking leave without permission. 1. Great Britain. Army.
    - ALS to [William Blathwayt], Gravesend, 1694/5 Jan 4
      Concerning quartering of troops. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - St. John, Henry St. John, 1st Viscount, 1652-1742
    - Signature, cut from the fly leaf of a book, 1678
  - Saxony (Electorate. 1356-1806) Laws, statutes, etc.
    - 3 documents relating to the Electorate of Saxony (in German), Dresden, 1693 Mar 13- (Box 8, Folder 166)
      - Including a representation of the, May 1
      - Chancery of the Electorate and two minutes relating to the marching of the Elector's troops. Endorsed by Blathwayt.
        See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 241
  - Saxony, Lower
    - "Declaration of the Directors of the Circle of Lower Saxony": contemporary ms. copy, Vienna, 1698 Dec 13/23
      Endorsed by Blathwayt.
  - Scarborough, Richard Lumley, 1st Earl of, 1650?-1721
    - 2 LS to William Blathwayt, n.p., 1691 Dec 31 (Box 8, Folder 167)
      - Arranging special pay for two, 1697/8 Feb 23
      - officers in his regiment. 1. Great Britain. Army.
    - AL to William Blathwayt, Camp at Tronken, 1692 Oct 4
      Requesting orders by express for his troops. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - Scarlati, Abbe
    - LS (in French) to [William Blathwayt], Varsame, 1697 Dec 31
      Reporting on French relations with Poland and various German states. 1. France--Foreign relations--Poland.
  - Scheel, M.
    - LS (in French) to William III, London, 1693 Mar 14 (Box 8, Folder 168)
      Endorsed by Blathwayt "Memorial of Mons. Scheel concerning the wisdom of Solomon." Scheel's intent was to receive reparations for English piracy against Danish ships. 1. William III, King of Great Britain, 1650-1702. 2. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Denmark.
  - Schonenberg, Francis
    - 2 memorials (extracts, in Spanish) to the constable of the Madrid castle, Madrid, 1694 Feb 25
      - At this time Schonenberg was the, 1695 Aug 16
      - Dutch envoy and represented England unofficially. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Spain.
    - 3 LS (in French) to William Blathwayt, Madrid, 1701 Jul 14-
      - Writing as English envoy on Spanish, Oct 20
      - affairs. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Spain.
  - Schuylenburg, Johann von der, Count, 1661-1747
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, 1702 Jan 28 (Box 8, Folder 169)
      "Monsieur. Je me suis donné l'honneur suivant votre bon conseil..." Accompanied by "An abstract of moneys disburst & claimed by Mons Schuylenburg to the 31st Decr 1694", and a fragment of a draft letter from Blathwayt to Schuylenburg, 1702 Jun 19.
  - Schuylenburg, W. S.
    - 6 ALS (in French) to [William Blathwayt], The Hague, 1697 Jun 26-
      - Concerning payment of troops and, 1698 Oct 3
      - subsidies for allies. 1. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697.
  - Scotland. Privy Council
    - Orders for Danish troops in Scotland: contemporary ms. copies, Edinburgh, 1689 Oct 30
      - Instructions for the route by which, Dec 16
      - Danish troops were to march from Edinburgh to Glasgow and from Berwick to Edinburgh. 1. Denmark. Army.
        See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 242
  - Scott, Edward
    - 4 ALS to William Blathwayt, Guernsey, 1687/8 Jan 5- (Box 8, Folder 170)
      - Reporting several instances of, 1688 Sep 15
      - increasing disaffection to James II among both soldiers and citizens. 1. Guernsey--History.
  - Selwyn, William
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, n.p., [1695 or later]
      Request for extending his leave on account of his continuing ill health. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - Shakerley, Peter
    - 2 ALS to William Blathwayt, Chester Castle, 1686 Oct 25, 31
      Reporting on officers absent from and present in the Chester garrison. 1. Great Britain. Army.
  - Shrewsbury, Charles Talbot, Duke of, 1660-1718
    - LS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1695 Apr 10 (Box 8, Folder 171)
      The King has approved an increase in the daily allowance of M. de Mainbray.
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Grafton, 1697 Jun 12
      Recommending that James Cressett's commission as envoy be enlarged to include the Court of Brandenburg. 1. Cressett, James, 1655?-1710
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Whitehall, 1697 Aug 13
      His illness and political news.
    - Document (signed, copy, in French): Commission to Mr. Van der Meer, Whitehall, 1690 Apr 7
      Accompanied by another document, in Dutch, of the proceedings of the States General, 1690 Mar 6, relating to Van der Meer's position as commissioner of the funds for the Vaudois in Piedmont. 1. Van der Meer, Albert. 2. Netherlands (United Provinces, 1581-1795) Staten Generaal. 3. Waldenses--Piedmont.
  - Skelton, Bevil, fl. 1661-1692
    - Certificate of his oath as Envoy to the Princes of Brunswick and Lüneburg, [Exchequer], 1681 Dec 6 (Box 8, Folder 172)
      Oath not to demand unjust sums of expense money while envoy, attested by Fr. Crawley. 1. Great Britain. Exchequer. 2. Crawley, Francis, d. 1682.
  - Skutt, Benjamin
    - Document (signed): account of the customs farm for Barbados, 1671-74, 1674
      Certified by Skutt; accompanied by another copy, also certified. 1. Barbados--History.
  - Slanning, Nicholas, Sir, d. 1692
    - ALS to William Blathwayt, Shaftesbury, 1686 Nov 2
      Reporting a court martial against Lawrence Boyle for misdemeanors. 1. Great Britain. Army. Courts Martial.
  - Slingelandt, Simon van
    - 3 LS (in French) to [William Blathwayt], 1697 Jun 15-
      - Concerning the payment of troops., Sep 18
      - Slingelandt was the Grand Pensionary of Holland. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Netherlands. 2. Great Britain. Army.
  - Smith, Aaron, d. 1697?
    - ALS to James Vernon, n.p., 1694 Jun 12 (Box 8, Folder 173)
      About the importance of bringing evidence before the Grand Jury before the end of term for an indictment against Col. John Parker for plotting against the king. 1. Vernon, James, 1646-1727. 2. Parker, John, fl. 1676-1705.
  - Smith, John
    - LS to William Blathwayt, Greenwich, 1697 Aug 30
      Asking assistance in getting the consulship of the French Netherlands. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Netherlands.
  - Smyth, Charles
    - ALS to [William Blathwayt], Harwich, 1702 Jan 1
      From the mayor of Harwich about shipping horses to Holland from Harwich. 1. Harwich, England--Mayor.
  - Somaripa, Carlin de
    - Letter (copy) to Field Marshall Thüngen, Neüburg, 1696 Sep 27
      Reporting on troops in the Rhine valley. 1. Thüngen, Hans Carl, Freiherr von. 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689- 1697.
  - Southwell, Edward, 1671-1730
    - Collection of legal documents relating to disputed lands in Ireland: 4 items, 1700-22 (Box 8, Folder 174)
      James Waller, Lt. Gov. of Kinsale, bequeathed money to his children based on income from property under care of Southwell. The documents include Waller's will, 1700 Aug 9; a report by the Master of the Rolls, 1715; a legal opinion sent to Southwell by Francis Annesley, 1718 Feb 3; a report on the case brought by Waller's daughters against Southwell, 1721; and a petition to the Master of Rolls by Southwell as defendant, 1722 Jul 6. I. Waller, James. II. Annesley, Francis.
    - Letter (copy) to the Navy Commissioners, Spring Garden, 1704 Sep 4
      About building a new shipping yard at Kinsale. 1. Great Britain. Navy Commissioners.
    - Notes on his efforts to purchase a life patent for a position in the Crown Office for his son: holograph, 1715 Aug
  - Spicer, Giles
    - ALS to [William Blathwayt], Gravensbrooke, 1702 Aug 10/21 (Box 8, Folder 175)
      "Sr. I beg you: pardon, in not riteing to you in all this time..."
  - Sprat, Thomas, Bishop of Rochester, 1635-1713
    - Letter (copy) to the Ecclesiastical Commissioners, n.p., 1688 Aug 16
      Resigning from the commission because he will not sit in judgment on those who refused to read the Declaration of Indulgence. Printed in 1688/9 as The Lord Bishop of Rochester's Letter, Wing S 5034. 1. Great Britain. Ecclesiastical Commission, 1686-1688.
  - Squibb, Robert
    - LS to William Blathwayt, Treasury Chambers, 1691 Jun 5
      Writing on behalf of the Lords of the Treasury for Blathwayt draw up a warrant for payment by Charles Fox and Thomas Coningsby to refund the Marquis La Barre his expenses for getting Danish recruits. 1. Fox, Charles, d. 1713. 2. Coningsby, Thomas Coningsby, Earl, 1656?-1729. I. Great Britain. Treasury.
  - Stahremberg, T., Count
    - Letter (copy) to the King of Sweden, Holmiae, 1696 Aug 13/23
      Concerning the King's mediation in peace negotiations. 1. Sweden. Sovereigns, etc., 1660- 1697 (Karl XI). 2. Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.
  - Stanhope, Alexander, 1639-1707
    - Letter (copy) to [the Earl of Nottingham?], Madrid, 1693 Jun 28/ (Box 8, Folder 176)
      - Reporting the heavy losses inflicted, Jul 8
      - on English ships by the French fleet near Lagos. 1. Nottingham, Daniel Finch, 2nd Earl of, 1647-1730. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Great Britain--Foreign relations--France.
    - Letter (copy) to Lord Galway, Madrid, 1694 Jul 5/15
      News of Admiral Russell and the English fleet. 1. Ruvigny and Raineval, Henri de Massue de Ruvigny, 2nd Marquis of, 1648-1720. 2. Orford, Edward Russell, Earl of, 1653-1727. 3. Great Britain. Navy.
    - 12 ALS and 1 LS to [William Blathwayt], Madrid, 1695 Apr 4/14-
      - Reporting on Spanish and diplomatic, Sep 19/29
      - matters; movements of the English fleet, especially Russell's squadron; O'Donnell, Irish troops and the Catalonian campaign. 1. Great Britain--Foreign relations-- Spain. 2. Great Britain. Navy. 3. Orford, Edward Russell, Earl of, 1653-1727. 4. O'Donnell, Hugh Balldearg, d. 1704.
    - 8 ALS to William Blathwayt, Madrid, 1698 Aug 18/28- (Box 8, Folder 177)
      - Reporting on events in Spain, the ill, Nov 30/Dec 10
      - health of the King of Spain, and developments in the Spanish succession crisis. 1. Carlos II, King of Spain, 1661- 1700. 3. Spain--History--Charles II, 1665-1700.
    - 4 letters (copies) to Robert Yard, Madrid, 1698 Aug 20/30-
      - Reporting via Yard to the Lords, Oct 19/29
      - Justices on the ill health of Charles II of Spain and the arrival of Aylmer's squadron. 1. Yard, Robert. 2. Great Britain. Lords Justices. 3. Carlos II, King of Spain, 1661-1700. 4. Spain--History-- Charles II, 1665-1700. 5. Aylmer, Matthew Aylmer, Baron, d. 1720. 6. Great Britain. Navy.
    - Letter (copy) to James Vernon, Madrid, 1699 May 31/
      - Reporting the ill health of the King, Jun 10
      - the state of the Spanish government, and prospects for the Spanish succession. Accompanied by a copy of another Stanhope letter of the same date to an unidentified recipient. A short extract of Stanhope's letter is printed in Manon's Spain under Charles the Second, 1840, p. 140. 1. Vernon, James, 1646-1727. 2. Carlos II. King of Spain, 1661- 1700. 3. Spain--History--Charles II, 1665-1700.
    - Letter (copy) to the Earl of Jersey, Madrid, 1699 Jun 14/24 (Box 8, Folder 178)
      Reports the ill health of the Spanish king; Spanish preparations in the West Indies against the British; question of the Spanish succession. Extracts printed in Manon's edition of Stanhope's correspondence, Spain under Charles the Second, 1840, pp. 141-42. 1. Jersey, Edward Villiers, 1st Earl of, 1661-1700. 2. Carlos II, King of Spain, 1661-1700. 3. Great Britain-- Foreign relations--Spain. 4. Spain-- History--Charles II, 1665-1700.
    - 3 ALS to William Blathwayt, Madrid, 1699 Jul 2/[12]
      - Reporting on Charles II's health and, -20/30
      - the actions of the Spanish Council of State. The letter of Jul 6/16 is accompanied by a copy, in Spanish, of Stanhope's note to Don Antonio Ubilla and his reply concerning William III's arrival at the Hague. 1. Ubilla, Antonio. 2. Carlos II, King of Spain, 1661-1700. 3. Spain-- History--Charles II, 1665-1700.
    - 4 ALS and 1 LS to William Blathwayt, Madrid, 1699 Aug 3/13-
      - Reporting on papal support for Spain, Oct 12/22
      - against the Darien colony, Don Antonio Ubilla's representation against negotiations in Loo concerning the Spanish succession, and the king's health. The letter of Aug 3/13 is partially printed in Manon's Spain under Charles the Second, 1840, p. 145. A copy of Ubilla's representation, in Spanish, with two copies in French, is enclosed in the letter of Aug 17/27 and Stanhope's reply of Aug 24 concerning the imprisoning of an Irish friar, chaplain to the Spanish ambassador to England. 1. Ubilla, Antonio. 2. Darien. Scots' Colony. 3. Carlos II, King of Spain, 1661-1700. 4. Spain--History--Charles II, 1665-1700. 5. Great Britain. Treaties, etc., 1694-1702 (William III). 6. Great Britain--Foreign relations--Spain.
    - Letter (copy) to Robert Yard, Madrid, 1699 Aug 30/ (Box 8, Folder 179)
      - Concerning the health of the king and, Sep 9
      - the public demonstrations against the royal family. Partially printed in Manon's Spain under Charles the Second, 1840, pp. 147-48. 1. Yard, Robert. 2. Carlos II, King of Spain, 1661-1700. 3. Spain-- History--Charles II, 1665-1700.
    - Letter (copy) to Don Antonio Ubilla, [Madrid], 1699 May 10
      Diplomatic letter reporting English efforts to prevent the Scots from settling in Darien. Accompanied by two copies, one in Spanish and one in English translation, of Ubilla's reply on behalf of the King of Spain, received by Stanhope on 21 May 1699. Ubilla was Secretary of the Despacho Universal. 1. Ubilla, Antonio. 2. Darien. Scots' Colony. 3. Spain--History--Charles II, 1665-1700.
    - Memorandum of cipher used by Stanhope in his diplomatic correspondence: contemporary ms. (copy), [ca. 1700]
  - Stepney, George, 1663-1707